Part two of questions you have about Palestine and Israel but are too afraid to ask, let's go.
What's the difference between Gaza and the West Bank?
Okay, so if you missed our first video about Gaza, I've dropped it in the comments below,
but just remember this. Gaza and the West Bank are separate territories belonging to Palestinians,
but both are illegally occupied by Israel. Now, Gaza used to be controlled by Israeli troops,
but today it's just completely sealed off from the outside world. Israel restricts what goes in
and out and also prevents most people from leaving. But Palestinians in the West Bank live under direct
military rule while Israel systematically demolishes their homes and wipes out entire communities to
build illegal settlements. What are settlements? Any Jewish person from anywhere in the world who's
never even visited Israel can move there, become a citizen, and live in one of these Jewish-only
settlements built on stolen Palestinian land. This is totally illegal under international law because
an occupying power isn't supposed to settle its own citizens on occupied land. But it's been going on
for over 50 years and continues to this day, and that's kind of the point. Israel wants to settle
people in the West Bank so it can claim it as its own land. There's a reason why you hear people call
this an apartheid regime, and that's because to prevent Palestinians from actively resisting this
illegal occupation, Israel denies them their most basic human rights, like access to clean water
and the ability to peacefully protest. The list of abuses goes on and on. Palestinians can't even use
some of the same roads as settlers. They have to go through hundreds of roadblocks and checkpoints
that look like human cages. What's happening in the West Bank now? For years, settlers have violently
attacked Palestinians and their property in an effort to get them to leave, and they're almost never
charged with a crime. And deadly attacks on Palestinians hit an all-time high in the West Bank
in 2022. Israeli soldiers who enforce martial law there protect settlers from any potential
Palestinian resistance to these attacks. So while the world's been watching Gaza, the West Bank's been put
on lockdown, and settlers are increasingly attacking and killing dozens of Palestinians.